"The Side Effects Statins: Are They Worth It?"
In my last video, I tried
to quantify the benefits
of starting cholesterol-lowering
statin drugs,
but that’s only half
the equation.
The number one reason people
may refuse to take statins
or stop taking them
is a concern about side effects.
Statins are considered mandatory
for secondary prevention,
for those with known
cardiovascular disease
to prevent a second heart attack
or stroke,
but primary prevention,
trying to prevent
our first event,
is more of a gray area.
A hundred adults
between the ages of 50 and 75
without known
cardiovascular disease
would have to be treated
with a statin for 2.5 years
to prevent one major
adverse cardiovascular event,
like a stroke
or a heart attack.
That’s the upside.
The downside,
if you treated 10,000
such people for a year,
the statins
would be expected to cause
fifteen cases
of muscle symptoms,
eight cases
of liver dysfunction,
twelve cases
of kidney dysfunction,
and 14 more eye conditions,
while at the same time
preventing 19 heart attacks,
nine strokes,
and eight cardiovascular deaths.
So, approximately the same risk
of having a major side effect
or a major benefit,
but a benefit like preventing
a heart attack or death
is more important than avoiding
a case of blurred vision;
so, these reviewers suggest
cardiovascular benefits
of statins
outweigh adverse effects
in primary prevention.
But wait.
There were only 15 cases
of muscle symptoms
out of 10,000 people treated?
That is based on
the clinical trials
that found approximately
one in a thousand users
over a ten-year period
develops serious muscle disease.
Cases of muscle weakness
or muscle breakdown
are hard to miss,
whereas the incidence
of statin-induced muscle aches
and pains
is far more contentious.
Such randomized
controlled trials
may seriously underestimate
adverse effects
like muscle pain,
since industry-sponsored trials
include these run-in periods
before the study even starts
to exclude people
who can’t tolerate the drugs;
so, no wonder they see
such low rates
in the actual trials where
all those folks who suffered
never made it into the trials
in the first place.
Furthermore, the majority
of clinical trials
don’t systematically ask
if people are experiencing
side effects,
since the trials are often run
by the company that makes them;
so, there’s an incentive
to "don’t ask, don’t tell."
Observational studies
out in the real world,
on the other hand,
don’t find muscle symptoms
in one in a thousand,
but rather one in ten
or even one in five,
that’s one or two hundred
times higher rates
than seen in the trials.
Some have attributed
this difference
between observational
and experimental studies
to the nocebo effect,
where patients experience
side effects they are expecting,
but it’s really
all in their head.
Or it could be because nearly
all trials never actually asked,
and even when they did ask,
industry-sponsored trials
are known to underreport,
known to sweep adverse effects
under the rug.
Finally, statin trials
have often excluded patients
with a history
of muscle problems,
who may be in the population
most at risk.
How do we get to the bottom
of this?
Well, if you
rechallenge patients
who claim
to be statin intolerant
with the real thing
or a placebo,
you can see what proportion
have muscle aches
that are actually caused
by the drugs,
and when you do that,
between 1/3 and 1/2 of patients
consistently report muscle pain
on statins but not placebo.
So, yes, a lot of people
who think statins
are causing their muscle pains
are actually mistaken,
but, at the same time,
a lot of people
really are suffering
because of these drugs.
The European
Atherosclerosis Society
estimates the overall risk
of developing
statin-related muscle symptoms
to be anywhere from 1 in 14
who go on statins
to nearly one in three.
Most trials
also don’t systematically ask
about other potential
adverse effects like fatigue,
even though fatigue
is among the most commonly
reported problems
by patients on statins.
In a non-industry-funded trial
on the effects of statins
versus placebos,
on energy and fatigue
with exertion,
effectively 4 out of 10
treated women
cited worsening
in either energy levels
or exertional fatigue.
What about effects
on the brain?
In 2012, the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration
issued a new warning
for the labeling of statin drugs
regarding potential
adverse effects on cognition,
including memory loss
and confusion.
That was based
on early studies like these,
but, thankfully,
more recent evidence
does not strongly support
a link
between statins
and cognitive impairment.
By 2015, putting all
the relevant studies together,
a systematic review
concluded that statin therapy
did not appear
to be associated
with cognitive impairment,
but again,
that’s from clinical trials.
What about statin use
and dementia risk?
Dozens of studies,
involving a total of more
than seven million patients,
found that statin use
was linked to lower risks
of dementias,
like Alzheimer’s disease.
This could be because
of the role cholesterol plays
in the development
of Alzheimer’s,
as I’ve explored before,
but it also could be due to
things like "healthy user bias,"
where people
who diligently take statins
may also engage in other
health-promoting behaviors,
and it’s those behaviors
that reduce the risk
rather than the drugs
themselves.
In the Alzheimer’s video,
I profiled Dr. Dean Ornish’s
landmark 2024 study
showing that a whole food
plant-based diet
and other
healthy lifestyle behaviors
could apparently reverse
the progression
of early-stage
Alzheimer’s disease
similar to his previous work
showing that a similar
plant-based diet and lifestyle
could reverse the progression
of heart disease,
but it doesn’t have to be
all or nothing.
In the Lyon Diet Heart Study,
heart attack survivors
were randomized to advice
to eat a more
Mediterranean-style diet
rich in plant-based omega-3s
or to just continue to eat
whatever their doctors
told them to eat.
And the dietary advice group
ate more bread, more fruit,
less ham and sausage
and other meat,
less butter and cream,
and though they didn’t
significantly change
their fish consumption,
they did eat more
of a provided butter-less spread
enriched with
plant-based omega-3s,
like the kind found
in flaxseeds and walnuts.
And check out
those survival curves.
Over the next five years,
only about 5% of the people
in the diet group
suffered a fatal
or nonfatal heart attack,
compared to more than 20%
of the control group.
Health professionals,
the pharmaceutical industries,
and research funding
and regulatory agencies
are almost totally focused
on lowering cholesterol levels
using drugs,
so it’s heartening to see
a well-conducted study
find that relatively simple
dietary changes
achieved greater reductions
in the risk
of all-cause mortality
and heart disease mortality
in a secondary prevention trial
than any of the drug studies
to date.
Diet beat out drugs
when it came to death.
Despite the striking findings,
we’re talking 70% reduction
in the risk of premature death
from just eating
more plant foods
and less meat and dairy.
Few cardiologists
may even be aware of the study,
even though it was published
in one of the most prestigious
medical journals
in the world.